Phillip: So why is it important to
have product or service knowledge?
Maddy: Well let’s think about
this by using an example.
Imagine you go to a computer
shop to buy a new laptop.
You want it to be able to be powerful enough
for streaming and gaming, to have good
battery life, a cutting-edge graphics card
and a host of other up to date functions.
But when you get to the shop and ask the staff
about the products and which one best meets your
specifications, none of them seem to be able to
answer your questions, and they don’t have any
real knowledge, only what’s written on the label!
Phillip: In most cases you wouldn’t be very
impressed and would choose to go elsewhere,
where you can get that advice and service.
This example demonstrates how important it
is that you have the appropriate knowledge
of the product or services that you provide
when dealing with people outside of your team.
Maddy: So, who are those outside your team?
These will probably be internal
and external customers.
• Internal customers are members of the same
organization as you, who rely on the service
or product being available for them to do
their jobs, such as a salesperson who needs the
product to be finished, so they can sell it.
• An external customer is someone outside
of your organization, who is interested
in purchasing your product or service.
Phillip: There may also be situations where
superiors within your organization, regulators,
or law enforcement may come to you, to find
out more about your product or service.
Maddy: Knowledge of your product
and services allows you to give a
positive impression of your team.
It shows that you and your team
take what they do seriously.
It shows that the team takes the time to
understand what it is they’re doing and how
it relates to people outside of the team too.
This makes the team look more professional,
showing that they’re engaged with their
work and are enthusiastic about it.
This not only reflects well on how the
team works, but it makes the product
or service appear more desirable too.
Phillip: Imagine if you were eating
in a restaurant and you asked what the
specials were for that day, only for
the waiter or waitress to just say,
“Oh!
I never bother to check the
specials, they’re never that good…”
It would make it look like the team
in that restaurant don’t care about
what they’re doing, that they want to
undermine each other, and it will probably
make you unlikely to eat there again.
Maddy: Having good knowledge of your
product or service also makes it more
likely that internal and external customers
will be able to get what they want.
If the service or product they enquire about
initially, isn’t suitable for them, wouldn’t
it be great if you knew that you could supply
one, that was a closer fit, to meet their needs?
Maybe the product or service is
unavailable, but with your help and
advice an alternative can be found.
Phillip: And remember, even if you don’t have
anything suitable for them, the fact that you
showed knowledge and passion for the product
or service you provide, this will impress
them and make them more likely to come to
you in the future, if their needs change.
Maddy: It also demonstrates that your team is
made up of people who are engaged with high
morale, and who care about their job, team,
and the product or service they provide.
They want to make that experience for the customer
both internal and external, a positive one and
by having good knowledge you can help to do this.